A finding aid to the Hildreth Meière papers, 1901-2011, bulk 1911-1960 in the Archives of American Art AAA.meiemari
Archives of American Art
Hildreth Meière papers
bulk 1911-1960
1901-2011
AAA.meiemari
Archives of American Art
23.2 Linear feet
The papers of Hildreth Meière measure 23.2 linear feet and date from 1901 to 2011, with the bulk of material dating from 1911 to 1960. The collection documents Meière's life and travels, and her long and prolific career as a muralist and mosaic artist through biographical material, correspondence, writings, thirteen diaries, files regarding her war relief work during the Spanish Civil War and World War II, printed materials, extensive photographs and slides, eight sketchbooks, and two videocassettes and nearly 100 motion picture films documenting her travels, artwork, and home movies.
Meiere, M. Hildreth, d. 1961
Biographical/Historical note
Hildreth Meière (1892-1961) was born in Flushing, New York, and had a prolific career as an architectural muralist and designer of mosaics and stained glass from the 1920s to the 1950s. Meière was educated at New York’s Convent of the Sacred Heart, Manhattanville, the Art Students League in New York, the California School of Fine Arts (now San Francisco Art Institute), and the School of the Art Institute of Chicago, in addition to pursuing studies in Italy. Meière had one daughter, Louise Meière, later Dunn, during a short-lived marriage that was later annulled.
In her day, Meière became noted as an Art Deco muralist (in paint and mosaics) and designer of stained glass windows; she created numerous images to embellish major public buildings and churches. Her major commissions include the Nebraska State Capitol at Lincoln, the National Academy of Sciences, the Resurrection Chapel of the National Cathedral in Washington, D.C. In New York, she designed the Art Deco plaques on the exterior wall of Radio City Music Hall; created mosaic interiors for the Irving Trust Building at 1 Wall Street; and provided ecclesiastical decorations for St. Patrick’s Cathedral, St. Bartholomew’s Episcopal Church, Temple Emanu-El, and elsewhere. She also created murals for the Chicago 1933 Century of Progress Fair, and the 1939 New York World’s Fair.
She was also an active officer in the Art Students League and the National Society of Mural Painters. Some of her most inspired collaborations were with the architect Bertram Goodhue in the 1920s, and only his sudden death in 1924 put an end to them, although some projects were finished with the successor firm.
Meière died in 1961 at the age of 68. Her work is remembered in several major publications, including The Art Deco Murals of Hildreth Meière by Catherine Coleman Brawer and Kathleen Murphy Skolnik, with photographs by Meière’s granddaughter, Hildreth Meière Dunn, published in 2014; and the catalog of the 2009 exhibition at St. Bonaventure University, curated by Brawer and photographed by Dunn, entitled Walls Speak: the Narrative Art of Hildreth Meière.
Scope and Contents note
The papers of Hildreth Meière measure 23.2 linear feet and date from 1901 to 2011, with the bulk of material dating from 1911 to 1960. The collection documents Meière's life and travels, and her long and prolific career as a muralist and mosaic artist through biographical material, correspondence, writings, thirteen diaries, files regarding her war relief work during the Spanish Civil War and World War II, printed materials, extensive photographs and slides, eight sketchbooks, and two videocassettes and nearly 100 motion picture films documenting her travels, artwork, and home movies.
Biographical material includes an autobiographical narrative written by Meière, her many awards and certificates, membership information, passports, her U.S. Navy service records from World War I, documentation of her brief marriage and family genealogy, obituaries, and memorial service documentation. Also found are extensive writings and research conducted by Meière's daughter, Louise Meière Dunn, which include a complete list of Meière's commissions, detailed biographical narratives, and records of Meière's works held elsewhere.
The papers contain Meière's personal and family correspondence, travel correspondence, and business correspondence regarding professional activities. Much of the correspondence with family and friends was written during Meière's extensive travels over the world. Both family and travel correspondence have extensive indexes, summaries, and in some cases, transcripts prepared by Meière's daughter, Louise Meière Dunn. Writings include poetry and diaries kept during childhood and school years, travel diaries, essays and talks written about Meière's work, writings Meière prepared for committees of the National Mural Painters Association, and detailed travelogues of her trips to Constantinople and the Balkans in 1933, to Russia in 1936, her "Grand Tour" to Australia, Southeast Asia, India, Africa, and Europe in 1952-1953, and her "Holy Land" tour of the Middle East in 1954.
Civilian War Service Records document Meière's efforts at war relief organization during and after the Spanish Civil War and during World War II. The Spanish Civil War files include extensive photographs provided by the Spanish government as well as three motion picture films documenting refugees and damaged architecture and public artwork shot by Meière during a trip sponsored by Franco's government. World War II activities concern Meière's efforts to organize artists in the United States to design and execute murals and other works of public art at military facilities around the U.S.
Travel records include maps, ephemera, slides, and 83 motion picture films taken on trips abroad between 1933 and 1958. Trips include Eastern and Western Europe, the Mediterranean Region and the Middle East, South America, Mexico and Guatemala, India, Sub-Saharan Africa, Southeast Asia, Australia, New Zealand, Scandinavia, and the UK. The motion picture films are mostly shot in Kodachrome color and many contain intertitles prepared by Meière to identify locations for travel lectures.
Printed materials consist primarily of clippings and publications that reference Meière's work, contain profiles of her, or contain published writings by her. Additional photographs and moving images include personal photographs of Meière, with portraits by Peter A. Juley and Sons and Berenice Abbott, photographs of many of her commissioned works, and a few photographs of artwork by others. Among the photographic documentation of artworks by Meière and others are motion picture films of the 1939 New York World's Fair, the D.C. Municipal Building Frieze, and the 1937 Paris Fair; also found are 311 lantern slides and 201 glass copy negatives of her own completed works as well as murals she documented while traveling, notably murals in Norway and Oberammergau, Bavaria, taken in the 1930s.
Eight sketchbooks date to her early years as an art student and artist and include many figure studies, landscapes, and theatrical sketches made at home and abroad.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
A majority of the collection placed on deposit 2001 by Louise Meière Dunn, daughter of Hildreth Meière. The collection was donated incrementally by Dunn through 2012. Donations occurred 2001-2007, and again in 2010-2012.
Existence and Location of Copies note
Some of the motion picture films have been digitized for research access, including films shot in Spain in 1938, the documentary "The Making of a Triptych," and films of the 1939 New York World's Fair and Municipal Center Frieze in Washington D.C. The New York World's Fair and Municipal Center Frieze films have also been preserved on film, and projection prints of these reels are available for use in accordance with the Archives of American Art's collection loan policies.
Conditions Governing Access note
Use of original papers requires and appointment and is limited to the Archives’ Washington, D.C. Research Center. Glass plate negatives are housed separately and are closed to researchers. 84 reels of motion picture film are temporarily unavailable while they are being digitized. Contact Reference Services for more information.
Arrangement note
This collection is arranged in 8 series. Indexes, summaries, and transcripts prepared by Louise Meière Dunn that relate directly to archival materials in the collection are found throughout the collection with the material they describe. These indices are particularly rich in Series 2, Correspondence.
Series 1: Biographical Material, 1915-2003 (0.6 linear feet; Boxes 1, 14, OV18)
Series 2: Correspondence, 1901-2011 (3 linear feet; Boxes 1-4, RD19)
Series 3: Writings, 1904-1960 (1.3 linear feet; Boxes 4-5)
Series 4: Civilian War Service Records, 1938-2006 (0.7 linear feet; Boxes 5-6, 15, 28)
Series 5: Travel Records, 1933-1958 (Boxes 6-10, 15, 28-33, OV18)
Series 6: Printed Material, 1913-1998 (2.1 linear feet; Boxes 10-12, 15)
Series 7: Photographs and Moving Images, 1915-1966 (5.3 linear feet; Boxes 12-13, 16-17, 20-27)
Series 8: Sketchbooks, 1911-1922 (0.4 linear feet; Box 13)
Abbott, Berenice, 1898-1991; Dunn,, Louise Meière; Exposition internationale. (1937: Paris, France); New York World's Fair (1939-1940).; Peter A. Juley & Son.; United States. Navy.; Art commissions; Diaries; Mosaicists--New York (State)--New York; Motion pictures (visual works); Muralists--New York (State)--New York; Painters--New York (State)--New York; Photographs; Poetry; Sketchbooks; Slides (photographs); Spain--History--Civil War, 1936-1939; Transcripts; Travel; Video recordings; War relief; Women artists; World War I, 1914-1918; World War, 1939-1945
- Biographical Material, 1915-2003; Series 1; 0.6 Linear feet Box 1, 14, and OV 18
  Scope and Contents note
  Biographical material includes a variety of primary sources as well as detailed research into Hildreth Meière’s life and work by Louise Meière Dunn, daughter of Hildreth Meière. Documents include an autobiographical narrative written by Meière, numerous awards and certificates, a calligraphic drawing that was a gift from Harry Zee Hoffman, genealogical research, a legal brief concerning Meière’s marriage, passports, membership cards, U.S. Navy service records from World War I, a school transcript, and wedding dress designs and samples from a Paris designer. Extensive writings and research by Louise Meière Dunn thoroughly document Meière’s life and career through correspondence, documentation of archival holdings regarding Meière’s commissions held by other institutions, and biographical writings.
  - Autobiographical Narrative, circa 1937 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Awards and Certificates (Box 1)
    - American Institute of Architects Fine Arts Medal, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      Oversized item housed in OV 18
    - Architectural League Medal of Honor, 1928 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Church Architectural Guild of America Membership Certificates, 1958; 1941 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      Oversized certificates housed in Box 14
    - City of New York Appointments, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      Oversized certificates in OV 18
    - Manhattanville College Distinguished Service Award, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Manhattanville College Honorary Doctorate, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      Oversized certificate in Box 14
    - National Academy of Design Membership Certificate, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - United Daughters of the Confederacy Application and Certificate, 1915 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - War Department Commendation, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Chinese Calligraphic Drawing by Henry Zee Hoffman, circa 1950 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Oversized drawing housed in Box 14
  - Genealogy, 1951-1955 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Marriage to Richard A. Goebel, "Statement of Facts", 1937 January 16 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Art Students League Membership Card, circa 1916 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Obituary and Memorial Service Records, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Passports of Hildreth and Marie Meière (mother), 1922; 1927-1929 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - School Transcript, Columbia University Summer School, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - United States Navy Service Records, 1917-1921 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Wedding Dress Designs and Material Samples, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Louise Meière Dunn Writings on Hildreth Meière (Box 1)
    - "From Pavolova to the Cathedral Basilica of St. Louis; A Woman Before Her Time in a Man's World; Hildreth Meière 1892-1961", 2003 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - "Her Last Days; Hildreth Meière 1892-1961", circa 2000 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - "Hildreth Meière; Her Words and Mine", 2001 (Box 1, Folder 22-24)
  - Article about Louise Meière Dunn in Les Amies, 1994 October (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Louise Meière Dunn Research on Hildreth Meière (Box 1)
    - St. Bartholemew's Church, 1974; 1980 (Box 1, Folder 26)
      Contains photographs
    - St. John's Church, Buffalo, NY; and Bank of New York, 1996; 1993 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - St. Mark's Church, Mt Kisco, NY, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Westport Room, Fred Harvey Restaurant, Kansas City, MO, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Century of Progress, Chicago World's Fair, 1996-1997 (Box 1, Folder 30)
      Contains photographs, contact sheets, and negatives
    - Peter Juley Collection, National Museum of American Art, 1985-1993 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Oversized Awards and Certificates from Box 1, Folders 4, 7, and 8 (Box 14)
  - Oversized Drawing from Box 1, Folder 11 (Box 14)
  - Oversized Awards and Certificates from Box 1, folders 2 and 5 (Box OV 18)
- Correspondence, bulk 1916-1961; 1901-2011; Series 2; 3 Linear feet Boxes 1-4, RD 19
  Correspondence includes three groups of correspondence: personal, travel, and business. In addition to letters to and from Hildreth Meière, each group of correspondence also has a set of indexes, summaries, and/or transcripts prepared by Louise Meière Dunn. The indexes to the personal correspondence are particularly detailed, with many letters partially or fully transcribed.
  Personal correspondence is between Hildreth Meière and family members and close friends, and is arranged by correspondent name. Hildreth Meière’s letters to family written between 1906 and 1924 are arranged at the beginning of the series, along with their detailed indexes. Letters from Meière’s mother, Marie “Min” Hildreth Meière (MHM) from 1916 to 1924, and two letters from her father, Ernest Meière follow. A single letter from HM to her classmates dated 1911 is followed by extensive letters to friend Katherine Harvey, which are heavily illustrated by Meière, including a lengthy scroll on Japanese rice paper containing an illustrated letter. Correspondence is also found with Louise Harmon, her sister Lloyd in California in the 1940s, and an extensive set of letters from Meière to her daughter Louise, from 1940 to 1961. Additional personal correspondents include Nancy Basinger, Ethel Howe, Narcissa Thorne, and Clare Winthrop. Original documents are often annotated with circled numbers written in pencil which correspond to the numbers in the index. These numbers begin a new sequence for each year.
  Travel correspondence is also personal in nature, and is largely comprised of letters to family from Hildreth Meière while traveling abroad. Most files contain a listing of their contents prepared by the donor. One 1934 letter from Munich describes Adolf Hitler's appearance at a performance Meière attended in Oberammergau, Bavaria, and includes a complete transcript.
  Business correspondence contains letters to and from Meière regarding lectures, commissions, professional organizations, schools, competitions, and projects. Correspondence is with architects, designers, fabricators, potential clients, and teachers. Where a correspondent is associated with a particular project, that project is noted in parentheses. A subject index to the business correspondence prepared by Louise Meière Dunn is found at the beginning of the grouping. Subjects include correspondence regarding schools, newspapers and periodicals, Architects, World’s fair, Commissions, and Ships.
  Arrangement note
  Personal correspondence is arranged by correspondent. Travel correspondence is arranged chronologically. Business correspondence is arranged by correspondent, or in some cases, by project. Where indexes, summaries, or transcripts exist, they are arranged immediately before the materials to which they refer. There is significant crossover between personal and travel correspondence, but they are arranged separately to facilitate use of the prepared indexes. Additional correspondence concerning the Spanish civil war relief effort and organizing activities during WWII is found in series 4, Civilian War Relief Records.
  - Personal Correspondence (Box 1)
    - Hildreth Meière's Letters to Family (1916-1924) (Box 1)
      - Indexer's Notes, 2001; 1993-1995 (Box 1, Folder 32)
      - Index, Glossary, and Chronology, 1994-1995 (Box 1, Folder 33)
      - Index (1916-1918), 1993-1995 (Box 1, Folder 34)
      - Index (1919-1922), 1993-1995 (Box 1, Folder 35)
      - Index (1923), 1993-1995 (Box 1, Folder 36)
      - Index (1924), 1993-1995 (Box 1, Folder 37)
      - Letters, 1901-1916 (Box 1, Folder 38)
        Not indexed
      - Letters, 1916 January-February (Box 1, Folder 39)
      - Letters, 1916 March-May (Box 1, Folder 40)
      - Letters, 1916 May-June (Box 1, Folder 41)
      - Letters, 1916 June-July (Box 1, Folder 42)
      - Letters, 1916 July-September (Box 1, Folder 43)
      - Letters, 1916 September-November (Box 1, Folder 44)
      - Letters, 1916 November-December (Box 1, Folder 45)
      - Letters, 1916 December (Box 1, Folder 46)
      - Letters, 1917 January-February (Box 1, Folder 47)
      - Letters, 1917 March-September (Box 1, Folder 48)
      - Letters, 1917 September-December (Box 1, Folder 49)
      - Letters, 1918 January-February (Box 1, Folder 50)
      - Letters, 1918 March-May (Box 1, Folder 51)
      - Letters, 1918 May-July (Box 1, Folder 52)
      - Letters, 1918 July-November (Box 1, Folder 53)
      - Letters, 1919 March-July (Box 1, Folder 54)
      - Letters, 1919 July-December (Box 1, Folder 55)
      - Letters, 1920 January-February (Box 1, Folder 56)
      - Letters, 1920 February-May (Box 1, Folder 57)
      - Letters, 1920 October-December (Box 1, Folder 58)
      - Letters, 1921 January-December (Box 1, Folder 59)
      - Letters, 1922 January-April (Box 1, Folder 60)
        Contains un-indexed letter
      - Letters, 1922 April-December (Box 1, Folder 61)
      - Letters, 1923 January-April (Box 1, Folder 62)
      - Letters, 1923 April-August (Box 1, Folder 63)
      - Letters, 1923 September-November (Box 1, Folder 64)
      - Letters, 1923 November-December (Box 1, Folder 65)
      - Letters, 1924 January-July (Box 1, Folder 65)
  - Personal Correspondence (Box 2)
    - Marie H. Meière (mother) Letters to Hildreth Meière (1916-1924) (Box 2)
      - Transcripts and Chronologies, circa 2008; 1 Electronic discs (CD) (Box 2, Folder 1)
      - Letters, 1916 January-May (Box 2, Folder 2)
      - Letters, 1916 May-September (Box 2, Folder 3)
      - Letters, 1916 October-December (Box 2, Folder 4)
      - Letters, 1917 (Box 2, Folder 5)
      - Letters, 1918 January-May (Box 2, Folder 6)
      - Letters, 1918 June-December (Box 2, Folder 7)
      - Letters, 1919 January-May (Box 2, Folder 8)
      - Letters, 1919 June-December (Box 2, Folder 9)
      - Letters, 1920 January-April (Box 2, Folder 10)
      - Letters, 1920 May-December (Box 2, Folder 11)
      - Letters, 1921 January-March (Box 2, Folder 12)
      - Letters, 1921 March -June (Box 2, Folder 13)
      - Letters, 1921 July-December (Box 2, Folder 14)
      - Letters, 1922 January-March (Box 2, Folder 15)
      - Letters, 1922 April-June (Box 2, Folder 16)
      - Letters, 1922 July-December (Box 2, Folder 17)
      - Letters, 1923 January-February (Box 2, Folder 18)
      - Letters, 1923 March-April (Box 2, Folder 19)
      - Letters, 1923 May-June (Box 2, Folder 20)
      - Letters, 1923 July-August (Box 2, Folder 21)
      - Letters, 1923 September-October (Box 2, Folder 22)
      - Letters, 1923 November-December (Box 2, Folder 23)
      - Letters, 1924 January-February (Box 2, Folder 24)
      - Letters, 1924 March (Box 2, Folder 25)
      - Letters, 1924 April (Box 2, Folder 26)
      - Letters, 1924 May (Box 2, Folder 27)
      - Letters, 1924 June-July (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Ernst Meière (father) Letters to Hildreth Meière, 1931; circa 1924 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Hildreth Meière Letter to Classmates, circa 1911 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Hildreth Meière Letters to Katherine Harvey (Box 2)
      - Letters, circa 1910 (Box 2, Folder 31)
      - Letters, 1910; Illustrated letters in sketchbook (Box 2, Folder 32)
      - Letters, 1911 September-October (Box 2, Folder 33)
      - Letters, 1911 November-December (Box 2, Folder 34)
      - Letters, 1912 January-February (Box 2, Folder 35)
      - Letters, 1912 March-April (Box 2, Folder 36)
      - Letters, 1912 May-June (Box 2, Folder 37)
      - Letters, 1913-1915; Includes illustrated letter written on scroll, circa 75 inches long. (Box 2, Folder 38)
        Oversized illustrated letter housed in RD 18
    - Louise Harmon Letter to Marie H. Meière, 1920 April 14 (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - Louise Harmon Letter to Hildreth Meière, 1938 (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - Hildreth Meière Letters to Anne (Nancy) Basinger, circa 1946-1961 (Box 2, Folder 41)
      Includes letters of condolence from Basinger
    - Hildreth Meière Letters to Lloyd Meière Bowers (sister) and Other California Family, 1941-1942; 2011 (Box 2, Folder 42)
      Includes partial transcripts
  - Personal Correspondence (Box 3)
    - Lloyd Meière Bowers Letters to Hildreth Meière, circa 2011; 1940-1943 (Box 3, Folder 1-2)
      Includes partial transcripts on electronic disc (CD) in folder 1
    - Hildreth Meière Letters to Louise Meière (daughter) (Box 3)
      - Letters, 1940-1944; 2011 (Box 3, Folder 3)
      - Letters, 2011; 1940 (Box 3, Folder 4)
      - Letters, 2011; 1941-1942 (Box 3, Folder 5)
      - Letters, 2011; 1943 (Box 3, Folder 6)
      - Letters, 2011; 1944 (Box 3, Folder 7)
      - Letters, 1947 December; 2011 (Box 3, Folder 8)
      - Partial Transcripts (1948), circa 2012 (Box 3, Folder 9)
      - Letters, 1948 May-August (Box 3, Folder 10)
      - Letters, 1948 September-December (Box 3, Folder 11)
      - Partial Transcripts (1949), 2011 (Box 3, Folder 12)
      - Letters, 1949 January-September (Box 3, Folder 13)
      - Letters, 1949 October-December (Box 3, Folder 14)
      - Partial Transcripts (1950-1951), 2011 (Box 3, Folder 15)
      - Letters, 1950-1951 (Box 3, Folder 16)
      - Partial Transcripts (1953), 2011 (Box 3, Folder 17)
      - Letters, 1953 (Box 3, Folder 18)
      - Partial Transcripts (1954), 2011 (Box 3, Folder 19)
      - Letters, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 20)
      - Partial Transcrpits (1955), circa 2011 (Box 3, Folder 21)
      - Letters, 1955 (Box 3, Folder 22)
      - Partial Transcripts (1956-1957), 2012 (Box 3, Folder 23)
      - Letters, 1956-1957 (Box 3, Folder 24)
        Contains detailed itinerary for travel to Mexico
      - Partial Transcripts (1958), 2012 (Box 3, Folder 25)
      - Letters, 1958 (Box 3, Folder 26)
      - Partial Transcripts (1960-1961), 2011 (Box 3, Folder 27)
      - Letters, 1960-1961 (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - Letters of Condolence to Louise Meière Dunn, 1961 (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - Letters to Hildreth Meière from Various Correspondents, circa 1929-1940 (Box 3, Folder 30)
    - Ethel Howe Letters to Hildreth Meière, circa 1930-1931 (Box 3, Folder 31)
    - Narcissa Thorne Letters to Hildreth Meière, 1991; 1933-1937 (Box 3, Folder 32)
      Includes clippings
    - Clare Winthrop Letter to Hildreth Meière, 1937 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Travel Correspondence (Box 3)